Rhiannon: Children and young people
may need help with a wide range of
issues at different points in their
lives, and parents and carers may
also need help and advice to deal with
behavioural or other mental health
problems their child is experiencing.
For those experiencing mental health
problems GPs are often a starting
point, and they can give advice or refer
children and young people to counsellors
and therapists who will be able to
give more specialist assistance whether
this is through the NHS or privately.
Counsellors and therapists can also
be approached directly and there are
many organisations online that can
recommend or showcase these services.
Children and Young People’s Mental
Health Services or CAMHS as they
maybe referred to, cover all services
that work with children and young
people who have difficulties with
their mental health or wellbeing.
They include psychiatrists and
psychologists and primary health
care workers and specialists.
A referral to CAMHS for an assessment can
be via a parent or carer, the individual
if they are old enough, a GP or teacher,
or via a school or social service.
Getting help from a specialist
CAMHS is different dependent on
area and waiting times can vary.
Youngminds.org.uk is committed
to improving the emotional
well-being and mental health
of children and young people.
They campaign, research and aim to
influence policy and practice based on the
experiences of children and young people
they work with, as well as their families
and the professionals who support them,
to help them to develop better well-being.
Mind.org.uk is perhaps the most
well-known of all mental health charities.
Mind’s aim is to provide advice
and support to empower anyone
experiencing a mental health problem.
They campaign to improve services, raise
awareness and promote understanding
and offer specific information and
support for young people aged 11 to 18
who are going through a difficult time.
They also offer supported housing,
drop-in centres, crisis helplines,
talking therapies, employment
and training schemes, counselling
and befriending services.
Stem4.org.uk is a charity that
promotes positive mental health
in teenagers and those who support
them including their families and
carers, education professionals,
as well as school nurses and GPs.
through the provision of mental
health education, resilience
strategies and early intervention.
This is initially through the provision
of mental health education, resilience
strategies and early intervention,
provided digitally, through their website.
There are many other charities and
local initiatives involved in supporting
good mental well-being, and role of the
voluntary and community organisations
in supporting mental health issues,
plays a very important role and they
sit outside of clinical settings.
Some local areas may also provide
drop-in sessions or support groups
run by volunteers, where children
and young people can get together.
The good thing about the support
framework within the charity and volunteer
sector, for those with mental health
problems, are that they can influence and
participate in projects or activities.
Helping them to increased levels of
confidence and boost their self-esteem
also helping their mental well-being.